Good afternoon
everyone and welcome back to True Health
Tuesday.
My name is Maria Jose Haml and as
promised today we're going to do food
addictions and temperance.
So uh I welcome uh everyone who is
connected and I also invite you to share
this um presentation with your friends
and family so they they also connect
uh because I think this is going to be
very interesting for a lot of people.
Uh we're kind of putting together a lot
of information that we have been talking
about for a while. As you remember, we
had been talking about diabetes for a
while. We had been talking about the all
the different conditions that are
connected to diabetes. All the, if you
remember, all the different
complications
that come, you know, with the
pre-diabetes, with the insulin
resistance. So, these are things that
might even happen without diabetes.
Without the pre-diabetes, people might
not even know that they have insulin
resistance. If you don't remember what
we're talking about, I invite you to go
back and watch the previous
presentations.
But as we talked about the last
presentation that I gave, which was two
weeks ago, uh sometimes it's hard to put
together or to start these um these
changes in our lifestyle. And why is
that? So, we talked about self-control.
We talked about starting new habits,
but even that sometimes is hard. So,
today we're going to talk about a more
serious reason why that might be hard,
which is food addictions. And we're
going to talk about temperance
because that's uh well, that's something
important that we talk about in our
church, temperance.
and we're going to talk about that in
relation to food but also we're going to
go beyond that uh as well. Uh so to
start uh first we're going to pray and
then we're going to welcome everybody
who is connected
and then we're going to go straight into
our topic for today for true health
Tuesday. So let's start with prayer.
Let's uh I invite everybody to um uh bow
your heads and start with a prayer.
Okay. Dear heavenly father, thank you so
much for this opportunity to once again
get together and discuss very important
topics about how to take care of our
bodies.
And we ask for your blessing upon this
presentation and that everyone who needs
to hear this message may be able to uh
hear it that this me message may reach
those who need to uh hear this important
topic
uh and uh be with everyone who is
connected tonight and who will hear it
later in Jesus name we pray. Amen.
So tell us tell us where you're
connecting from. So welcome everybody
who is connected today. I'm not even
sure yet uh if I know how to tell by the
way this is the first time that I am
going to be somewhat in charge. It's a
little scary for me you guys. So wish me
luck or pray for me because this is new
thing for me you guys. So tell me where
you're connected from.
And uh thank you for connecting. Okay.
Thank you for s for being with us. I
always enjoy
uh your comments. So this is always
uh very enjoyable for me when you put
your input. That's very very good um for
me because I think it's very very
important that we all connect. Okay,
that we participate.
So let's uh begin. Well, as you as you
know, I always begin saying that what
we're going to talk about, a lot of it
is, you know, scientific. A lot of it
has to do with might, it might even
sound medical, but it's not meant to be
medical advice.
So, I just want to let you know this is
all educational.
And as you also know, I always start off
by saying, some of you already know, you
know, I've already told you in the past
that uh and and some of you are already
are already know this, but some of you
might be connecting for the first time.
This is why I always repeat it that I
always my rule is always Isaiah 8:20.
Many of you hopefully also go by this
rule as well which is to the law and the
testimony. If they
speak not according to this word is
because there is no light in them and I
apply this to health. I hope you do too.
So when you hear things out in the
world, in the uh internet, social media,
wherever, make sure I recommend you
apply this rule to everything. Okay? Um
so that you are keep your eyes open and
so that everything you hear regarding
health,
nutrition,
everything needs to be according to the
law and the testimony which
the way I interpret I hope you interpret
it as well is the Bible and the spirit
of prophecy. I hope you remember that
too.
and that um also I believe in this that
everything needs to be a science have a
scientific basis. All right. And to me
what you're looking at on the screen,
let's change it like this so you can see
it bigger. Um this is the hierarchy. So
the lowest level over here is the lowest
level of scientific
um evidence. So when you just hear
people talking and give it their opinion
on social media for instance that's not
your best uh source of evidence. Okay.
You you want to look at good uh
scientific evidence is the top level. Do
you see the top level? Those are good
that's good type good kind of scientific
evidence.
Okay. So now let's
uh also remind you here's another one
that I think this is all review for many
many of you
is science what Ellen White has says
about had said about science you know I
think I've said this in the past that
people have told me in my own YouTube
channel why do you say why do you use so
much science we have the Bible okay yes
we do for us believers the Bible is
number one but sometimes times we get to
talk to people who are not believers.
So yes, we know that the Bible is number
one in our lives, but when you talk to
people who are not believers,
it's not going to be their number one.
And also look at what Ellen White said.
A knowledge of science of all kinds is
power
because God is the creator of science.
Science is empower and science and the
Bible are not against each other
and it is in the purpose of God that
advanced science
shall be taught in our schools as a
preparation for the work that is to
preede
the closing science of earth uh the
closing scenes of earth's history when
that might be when do you think that
might be happening
do you think now Maybe I think
a practical knowledge of the science of
human lives is necessary
in order to glorify
who?
Who?
God.
And I ask you one thing
is glorifying God part
of the first angel me first angel's
message. What do you think is glorifying
God part of the first angel's message? I
think it is. That's my opinion, but I
think it's uh also supported by the uh
word of God. All right. This is all
review as you remember, but this one I
don't know if you remember this slide
from last time.
This is a review from last presentation.
You might or might not have seen it.
This is also going to be important for
this presentation. Okay,
please put your eyes on the screen
because this is going to be very
important for today's presentation as
well. Look at the top.
One of the strongest temptations
that man has to meet is upon the point
of what?
What's that word?
Appetite.
One of the strongest temptations that
man has to meet is upon the point of
appetite. This is in the book Councils
on Diet and Food.
Quote number two, Satan is constantly on
the alert to bring the race fully
under his control.
Fully under his control. And now look at
this statement.
Look
his strongest.
That is a very very important word. his
strongest hold on man. Not his number
two number two strongest hold on man.
His strongest hold on man is through the
appetite.
His strongest hold on man. I'm just
emphasizing this because this is
extremely important for today. This was
written over a hundred years ago, but I
think it's more true today than what it
was a 100 years ago.
His strongest hold on man is through the
appetite. And this he seeks to stimulate
in every possible way.
Wow. I don't know about you, but I think
this is true. even more today than it
was 100 years ago. I don't know what you
think. What do you think?
Wow, we have people from I'm barely
looking at the chat. Sorry you guys from
Greece and Rancho Cukamonga. So,
welcome you guys. Me from Greece and
Eric from Rancho Cukamonga.
So, welcome everyone. All right, let me
read the third the third one. The
controlling power of what you guys
appetite
will prove the
I hope you're reading with me. the ruin
of thousands.
When
if they had conquered on this point,
they would have had the moral power to
gain the victory over every temptation
of Satan.
Hello, Robert from Labot, Texas. Welcome
everyone. Welcome.
Ruin. Yes. Ruin. Ruin. Ruin. Are you
reading this with me?
Do you see how important?
Do you believe that this is more true
today than it was 100 years or over 100
years ago when this was written?
I hope I hope you're paying attention.
I don't know if you believe it too, but
I think it I don't know.
Oh,
a popupka. Is that how you say a popup
club? Florida. Jeff, thank you for
joining us. Jeff, amen and amen. Yes,
Robert. I think so, too. Now,
appetite. Okay. Today we're going to
talk about very I think it's very
serious because we were talking about
last uh presentation about self-control
how to build habits to apply all the
things that we have talked about in the
previous four presentations regarding
diabetes pre-diabetes insulin resistance
and how all those things are connected
to all of the complications of insulin
resistance which include hypertension
high cholesterol obesity and all the
different things, you know, even fatty
liver, all those things. And why is it
so hard sometimes? Because I worked as a
nutritionist at a clinic. And I would
counsel people on nutrition,
and I would do the questionnaires, you
know, the 24-hour recalls, all these
different things. I ask people about
their diets and see, you know, people
eat junk food all the time, drink sodas,
eat chips, you know, eat fast food, all
these things.
You think people didn't know that this
was junk food?
Yeah, I could tell you 99% of people
know that junk food is junk.
You think people don't know?
You don't You think people don't know
soda is bad for them or that burgers are
junk food? People know.
So why? And also remember when we talked
about
uh uh I don't know if you remember but
we we we talked about a doctor that was
studying like cigarettes and he himself
smoked also and he this was a doctor
that discovered that smoking caused
uh uh lung cancer back in the 30s and
40s. Do you remember that?
Why is it so hard to do what we know
that is good for us? In fact, this isn't
the Bible. Even Paul talked about it.
Where is it?
The good that I know to do, I don't do.
Where is that? Some of you know.
Tacoma, Washington, Wendell Vines, thank
you for joining us. Thank you.
Good welcome everyone. But where does uh
Paul talk about this his own struggle
with this where
if you know put it in the chat
today we're going to talk about what is
addiction
because what I'm going to talk about is
food addiction in particular but it
applies to all addictions. Romans 7.
Yes, Robert. Thank you.
The uh verse is Ro is Romans 7 uh 19. Uh
Romans 7:19.
He himself struggled with this. The good
that I know that I need to do, I don't
do. And the bad thing that I know that I
can't that I should not do that I do.
Yes or no? Don't we all struggle with
that? Yes or no?
We know we need to stop eating junk
food,
stop drinking the soda, start eating
more salads,
go for walks,
and we don't do it. Why is it so hard
for a lot of people? It's a food
addiction in terms of the um the
nutrition aspect of it. I know that
I myself am food addict. I guess
recovered or recovering because you know
we should never claim victory over
things that are always addictive
right I think now what is an addiction
I'm going to say this
whether it's food cigarettes drugs
alcohol it's all the same thing
even behavioral addictions as you know
because there's such a thing as a
substance addiction addiction, substance
use disorder as they call it. Now, you
can be addicted to a substance such as a
tobacco, you know, there's nicotine in
it. Alcohol, that's a substance. A drug
is a substance, but there's also such a
thing as behavioral addictions as you
know. You know, here the picture might
show something like an internet
addiction. I I would say today social
media could be an addiction. But the one
recognized
formally in the DSM, the you know the
book about you know um mental disorders
or whatever is gambling. Gambling is an
addiction formally recognized as uh as
an addiction and it's it's not a
substance. Obviously you don't eat
gambling, right? So it's not a
substance. It's a behavioral addiction.
So it's the same process in the brain.
All the addictions have the same sort of
you know five main categories
uh or characteristics I should say.
There's a number one irresistible a
irresistible compulsion
to continually use
this substance or continually behave.
Right? There's irresistible. you have to
do is compulsive
and there's a need to increase the
amount.
Your brain
is adapting to the small amount and then
needs more and more and more which leads
to a dependence.
A dependence your we'll talk about why
that happens. It's a it's it's a brain
thing. Okay. Your your brain is there's
neural adaptations. We're going to talk
about what that is.
And number four,
there's a high tendency to relapse. As
you might already know,
my dad tried to quit smoking
a million times. In fact, there's
science that says that smokers need to
try about 30 times. I remember reading
that. Also, laziness, convenience.
Yes, also laziness. think that is true
because you know that that's a that's a
very true statement Emmy thank you
if you're running out of time that's why
we talked about planning last
presentation right because you know okay
if you haven't planned if you haven't
planned your meals that's why planning
is so important okay so if you haven't
planned your meals for the week and here
you you are at work it's 1:30 2:00 p.m.
and you're running out of time and you
you're you're you're busy or whatever at
work and now you're hungry, you're just
going to go to the the drive-thru. What
are you going to do? It's much easier,
more convenient,
as Amy says,
to go to the drive-thru. It takes it
literally takes two minutes.
It's convenient. Okay. High tendency to
relapse. the literally it's
these um addiction um
programs, you know, treatments.
The rate of relapse is skyhigh, sky
high.
It's just terrible. Okay. And number
five, harmful effects either for the
individual or for society or both. I
would say alcoholism is probably the
worst when it comes to the effects for
society
as you probably already know that right?
You probably already know. Okay. So what
about food?
Can food be an addiction? Can food have
the same five characteristics we talked
about just right now? The five things I
just mentioned. Can food do that? Many
people would like, okay, no come. That's
an exaggeration.
What do you think?
Can food do that?
Those things I just said, can it cause
dependence?
An irresistible compulsion?
Can it have these, you know, the need to
increase the amounts, a tendency to
relapse? All these things. Is that an
exaggeration? Am I really exaggerating
these things? Now when we talk about
addictions, let's just talk about how it
happens. First of all, what you're
looking at here
is what they call the dopamine pathways.
This is how addictions happen in the
brain. Okay? This is the physiological
scientific way how addictions happen.
And what we're looking at here is the
part of the brain
where the neurons
that actually cause you to feel
pleasure
are located. Okay. So the pleasure you
absolutely Yes. Okay. So some of you
agree with me. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you. Yes. I think you're right.
Nowadays we have comfort food. Yes. No
wonder we call it comfort. It's in the
name.
Now that's a very interesting way you
you you that what you're saying right
here is very interesting. Comfort. It
gives us comfort.
Comfort.
Pleasure.
Where does that come from?
It comes from dopamine. As you some of
you might already know this, dopamine is
a neurotransmitter that helps us to feel
pleasure. Basically, that's what it is.
Bottom line, very simple.
Pleasure. Now, pleasure is not a bad
thing, you guys. It's normal. We have to
actually feel it because if we didn't
feel pleasure when we eat, we wouldn't
eat. If we didn't feel pleasure when we
have sex, we would never have it. We
would never reproduce. And the human
race would have finished by now.
Pleasure reward centers of the brain.
Exactly. It's something we absolutely is
normal. It needs to be felt.
It has it's necessary. It's normal in
the right amounts.
Okay. But what I want to um I want to
help you see is where these uh neurons
start, which is right here in the middle
in the middle. I don't know if you see
right there in the middle in the center
where the little circle is. And then
these neurons actually extend
extend to different parts of the brain
actually
like the prefrontal cortex the the the
part of the frontal lobe of the brain
and then other parts of the inner part
of the brain as you see. So these uh
neurons have extensions that are
actually very long and actually go to
these parts of the brain. And therefore
when these neurons
that cause pleasure or help us to cause
pleasure because they produce dopamine
when these neurons are overstimulated,
hear me out, overstimulated.
When they are overstimulated by things
that cause exaggerated amounts of
pleasure
artificially,
they can damage the parts of the brain
that you see here
that you see here that these
neurons reach.
And what what what happens in these
parts of the brain?
What happens? Look in the blue
parts of the preffrontal cortex.
This is a very important important part
of the brain right here in your frontal
lobe
has to do as it says right here in this
chart with motivation.
This is part of the brain where your
executive functions of the brain are
located.
It's also where inhibition is found. In
the green is where your re uh reward
prediction where your pleasure is. We
already talked about but in the also the
purple cognition,
cognitive control,
self-control.
The red learning and memory. That's
where habits happen. Learning and
memory. Habits.
All of this is damaged when these
neurons are overstimulated
sort of distribution. Yes, we humans
tend to abuse and remove restrictions
that are meant to help and protect us.
Yuber cow. Yubercow. I hope I'm saying
it right. That's a very interesting
name. Thank you for joining us. Welcome.
Now,
you know how neurons connect with each
other? You probably know there's a
connection between neurons.
They're not touching each other. There's
something called the syninnapse between
neurons. And there's actually a little
gap, the synaptic cleft. This is one
neuron. And this is the next neuron.
Right? So the the the space between the
neurons is called the synaptic clft. And
this is how the neurotransmitters are
passed on from one to another. They're
released from one neuron and passed on
to the next. And the way that the next
neuron catches the dopamine that's sent
from the last neuron to the next neuron.
The way that the next neuron catches it
is through the receptors.
And so you see down in the bottom here
it says dopamine receptor. Do you see
right here? Dopamine receptor is how the
dopamine is
absorbed so to speak by the next neuron.
That's how it's accepted by the next
neuron. Okay? Remember this because this
is how dopamine is passed on, how it's
um transmitted.
Remember that. Okay, this is how it's
distributed.
But what I want to say right now is that
this dopamine here, God made it. God
made it.
This is part of creation.
God made us to feel pleasure. It's not
that dopamine is bad. Dopamine in itself
is not a bad thing. In fact, do you know
or did you know
that the word Eden
Eden
as in the garden of Eden,
the word in Hebrew means pleasure.
We were made to feel pleasure in a place
of bliss, in a perfect place of beauty,
of happiness,
of pleasure,
but not extreme,
not perverted.
See, that's the problem. After the fall,
we perverted everything, including
pleasure.
God made us to feel normal pleasure.
What's normal pleasure? The pleasure
that we feel for instance when we read a
good book or when we eat our favorite
fruit
or when we hug our loved ones
when we go for a nice walk. These are
normal things that make us feel normal
amounts of pleasure.
Okay, normal. But human has perverted
everything. So when we engage in things
that are excessive
ex anything excess is bad but excess
there's things that stimulate the brain
in excessive ways.
They stimulate
the reward centers of the brain
excessively.
So the amount of dopamine you produce
with heroin
is way more than what you would produce
with even sex, which is probably the one
activity that gives us the most amount
of dopamine in normal situations.
And that overp production of dopamine is
damaging for the brain.
And the repeated action of that activity
that overstimulates the brain is
damaging for the brain.
So the brain has to protect itself from
that activity from that overp production
of dopamine. the brain put puts on the
brakes.
And what it does is
diminish the amount of those dopamine
receptors that I showed you a little
while ago. Remember the dopamine
receptors that I showed you?
The connection between the two neurons,
the dopamine receptors, what the brain
does takes them away. And that is what
it does to
lower the amount of dopamine in the
brain. So I want to show you something
interesting. Wait before that since 2021
COVID damaged my alactory bulb. Oh my.
I'm sorry to hear that. And food. Yes. A
lot of people had that.
I'm so sorry to hear that. Wow. I'm so
sorry to hear that. My lab work was
great. A1C, cholesterol, kidney
function. Oh, I'm glad it's better now.
is that I hope that's what you're saying
that you're better now. But a lot of
people lost their sense of smell and
taste because of COVID. CO is not a
respiratory disease. It's a systemic
virus. It causes damage in all tissues
potentially
because it's not a respiratory disease.
It's a systemic disease.
So I we still have to be careful with
it. That's the point. Okay, let me show
you something. Okay, what we just said
is that the brain has to protect itself
from over stimulation.
So, what you're looking at here is a PET
scan of the brain
uh in different situations.
So the extreme left is a normal brain
and the red the red shade
the red shade over here is the dopamine
receptors.
Dopamine receptors normal amount of
dopamine receptors all the way to the
left.
That's a normal brain.
The brain in the middle is of a person
who has been using cocaine for one
month.
Do you notice something in this brain?
Welcome Andrea from New Brunswick,
Canada. Thank you for joining our
presentation from New Brunswick.
I hope I said it right. Brunswick,
Canada. Do you notice here what's going
on with this brain in the middle? What's
happening?
Remember the red means dopamine
receptors?
What is going on?
What I mentioned just a minute ago is
that the brain has to put on the brakes.
When we engage in activities that
overstimulate the brain artificially,
whether it's a substance or a behavior,
what we said in the beginning of the
presentation is that there are two types
of addictions. It could be substance use
disorder is when we become addicted to a
substance or it could be a behavioral
addiction because gambling is not a
substance.
internet addiction, porn addiction.
These are not substances, but they are
just as addictive.
And they cause the same issue in the
brain.
What are you looking at here in the
middle?
What's missing are the
dopamine receptors. Why? Because the me
just said it, no dopamine receptors.
Why? Because the brain has to protect
itself
because it's it's a flood of dopamine.
It's too much.
It's exaggerated.
It's damaging.
So, the brain has to protect itself. So,
it puts on the brakes. It takes away the
dopamine receptors.
And what we see right here, right on top
of me, right here, four months of
cocaine, no dopamine receptors.
So there's no dopamine receptors. So
this is what happens you guys though.
Now this person
this person
unfortunately
when they eat a bowl of strawberries
when they go for a walk at on the beach
when they read a nice book they're not
going to feel any pleasure.
There's no way to feel pleasure anymore.
What are they going to need? They're
going to need that over stimulation
again. The only way to feel normal
is to use a drug.
The only way to feel normal is to use
the drug again.
Oh, I'm sorry. You're not better. Oh. Oh
jeez.
Your name your name is Herve. Ah, okay.
Thank you. Well, thank you and and uh
thank you for joining us and I'm so
sorry that you still haven't recovered
stopped you from eating the food you
used to eat. I'm so sorry. Jeez. Ah,
that's long term. I guess that's a form
of long co I guess. Jeez. So sorry. H
hope you recover someday. Some people it
last couple years a few years.
So here we see what has happened. Okay,
this is so so these are the stages. This
is how it happens. This is how it all
happens. The first time a person tries
a substance. Let's say they do it
because it's a choice. It's a choice the
first time, maybe the second, maybe even
the third. It's a choice. They're
seeking pleasure, right?
It's a very pleasurable thing to consume
heroin. I'm sure. I don't even know, but
I'm sure they get these this sense of
ecstasy,
euphoria.
It's an exaggerated amount of dopamine.
So, they repeat the action.
That dopamine makes them want to do it
again and again and again and again and
again and again. That repeated pattern
causes the loss of the dopamine
receptors.
It causes this tolerance over here right
says increased tolerance
the brain that's called the neuro
adaptation. The neuro adaptation is the
dopamine receptors going down down down.
So the brain starts to adapt,
tolerate
the substance more and more and more.
But now it becomes a dependence because
now it needs the substance just to feel
normal. That's what the addiction is.
It needs the substance just to feel
normal.
It's a dependence.
And guess what? It's not just heroin.
It's not just cocaine.
Obviously, alcohol, nicotine,
caffeine.
Let's be honest.
Let's be honest. I'm sorry. I don't mean
to offend anyone, but caffeine is a
dependence. Yes or no?
Some people need the two cups or else,
right?
It could be gambling. It could be porn.
What about food, you guys?
Can food be addicted?
What do you think?
Can food become a dependent? Sugar.
Sugar. Emmy. Thank you.
Let's look at
this comparison.
Let's look at this comparison.
Top left
normal brain.
Tolerance is mistaken for control, says
Robert.
going from I can handle my fun to now
the rabbit's got the
Yes,
you lose the control. You no longer have
self-control. That's right. That is
correct.
Self-control is gone.
Your brain is damaged.
The brain is literally damaged.
The self-control is this part of the
brain. And remember the the neurons got
to this part of the brain and this part
of the brain is literally damaged. All
right. Look at the top left normal
brain.
Top bottom cocaine user. Do you see it?
Do you see the cocaine user? What's
happening? Where are the dopamine
receptors? Are there any? What's
happening to dopamine receptors with
cocaine user?
Not there.
What's happened to the alcoholic over
here? Bottom right. Do you see very
little? Almost none.
Now look at the top right.
Brain of what
are you looking?
What do you see?
Maybe not all obese persons
have a food addiction,
but this person does.
This person does
because this person has no dopamine
receptors.
And I can tell you from the literature
just from the general population
20%
is what they have you know some research
has found 20% of the general population
has food addiction
amongst
uh the obese
50 plus
who knows
Most definitely. Yes. Food is an
addiction. We SDA never talk about
That's right. We never talk about it.
Even within the plant-based community,
I've gone to the conferences at American
College of Lifestyle Medicine and the
they they the public somebody in the
public asked the questions and I've
never seen a satisfactory
answer from presenters to this day.
They don't know how to handle the
question unfortunately.
Lord have mercy.
I know. Lord have mercy. So what I'm
seeing here from this and I think you
would agree
also here
is that food can definitely be
addictive.
And the the I'm telling you I wrote my
dissertation on this. I have over 360
um references.
There's plenty
of scientific research on this. And what
the research has found is that over
um overly
palatable food, what they call highly
palatable food, we're talking about
processed food, highly processed foods,
mostly highly processed foods, food that
has high amounts of three things more
than anything.
Fat,
sugar, and salt
in combination
are highly stimulating to the brain
to the same pathways
as addictive drugs and addictive
behaviors. The exact same pathways.
So the food manufacturers
know this.
These foods
are engineered. Obviously they are not
going to say, you know, the food
manufacturers are not dumb. They're not
going to say, you know, oh, we make
foods addictive. Well, they're not going
to say that.
No one is ever going to admit in the
food industry that they make the food
addictive. No one's ever going to say
that, you guys. Ever.
Ever.
But they know what they're doing.
They know what they're doing. They've
known it for decades.
Now, my question to you is, could this
be the reason why we have uh or at least
partly
the reason why we have
the obesity epidemic?
I don't know.
Do you think?
Oh, yeah. Cocaine is strikingly similar.
I don't know if you were here. Um, obese
and cocaine are strikingly similar. So,
last presentation, this is just review
from last presentation.
How many of you remember I talked about
this
study? This is just the headline. study.
Sugar hidden where?
Where? Where's the sugar hidden?
What kind of food?
Healthy food.
What does junk mean?
Junk means trash. Yes or no? I'm just
using the word. What's a synonym for
junk?
All right. Also, these foods right here
are not sweets.
I'm just saying. All right. Sugar hidden
where junk food is how many times?
How many times?
That can't be. Sounds like a huge
exaggeration, doesn't it? The media must
be exaggerating. Come on now.
Eight times more addictive than cocaine.
Nah.
Okay. Well, let's read the actual study.
Here you go. Take a picture.
Look it up. You can read the study.
It's not just
an exaggeration.
It's a study.
It's not the only one, by the way.
There's many. Here are the researchers.
I showed you this last time. There's a
little rat
and a a bag of Oreos.
I don't think they gave the rats Oreos.
This is just,
you know, for show. But and I remember
the cartoon I showed you last time.
It's illustrative of what happened. They
basically made the rats addicted to
cocaine first
and then once the rats were already
addicted to the cocaine, they put them
in some kind of enclosure
and then they gave them or they had both
the sugar and the cocaine available
to them.
And the rats went to the sugar eight
times more than to the cocaine even
though the cocaine was available and
they already were addicted to it.
That was the uh experiment.
And last time I also mentioned that in
nature
sugar and fat are never together.
Remember in nature they're not together.
You either have fat and seeds
and nuts and avocado
and olives and coconut. All of these
things have fat, natural fat with its
fiber, by the way, with other nutrients
like vitamins, minerals,
phyitochemicals, antioxidants
that act synergistically to give you
health.
And the fiber
protects you because the fiber carries
some of that fat out of your body. I
don't know if you knew that, but it's
true.
I don't think you should ever eat the
fat without its fiber.
It protects you.
Anyway, I digress. The sugar, same
thing.
The sugar comes with fiber.
It's never industrially refined
in nature.
It comes with
vitamins, minerals, phyitochemicals,
antioxidants.
The fiber protects you. It carries some
of the sugar out of your body. You
should never eat the sugar without its
fiber.
They never come together.
When you put them together,
it overstimulates the brain. That
mixture, you guys, is like a bomb
for your brain.
That's what processing does.
The processors, the the food
manufacturers, they know what they're
doing. They're not dumb.
They know.
By the way, I want to mention something
real quick. I always mention it in this
presentation.
I just wanted to
mention the levels of addiction we have
reached in this country and this is a
way to illustrate it. Okay.
Satan is subverted uh the humanity to
the point of appetite. Yeah. I hope you
saw the first u few quotations at the
beginning of the presentation. I read
those quotes about the appetite. So if
you haven't if you didn't connect early
enough, you can go later when it's
posted to the recording and watch watch
it at the beginning. Very interesting. I
love your curry. You can make curry
healthy. I think uh junk food. Yes. Yes.
Yes. Fasting is very very good. Yeah,
definitely. Uh someday I'll do a whole
presentation of fasting. Maybe that
could be my next presentation. H I'll
think about that. Could be it. Uh okay.
Yeah.
What was I going to say? Oh, yeah. Um,
okay. Illust, this is I think an example
of how bad things have gotten this
country, but this has been around for a
while. Okay. Did you know that in a
city?
I won't even say the city. I think you
know if I just say since city,
you know what city? There's a
restaurant.
Of course, this is just a theme, okay?
The theme of the restaurant just to it's
for purposes of, you know, uh being, I
don't know, provocative, just to draw
attention.
Uh but the name of the restaurant is
Heart Attack Grill.
Yeah, this is a place. It exists in Sin
City.
Uh and this is the menu, you guys.
The smallest burger is called single
bypass burger.
Don't go there. Okay.
Some of you are like, "Oo, that sounds
good." No. No. I know you don't. I know
you don't. Um
the the one with the two patties and two
pieces of cheese and two slices of bacon
or whatever.
It's the double bypass burger. Triple
that. It's called the triple bypass
burger.
quadruple bypass burger. And you know
what? This is just the menu they
publish, but you can go up to eight
literally. So, they have I don't know
the world
uh record for the most calories in the
world or something for their burger. I
think it's the one with the four patties
or six patties. Something like 9,000
calories. I'm not kidding. Look it up.
It's horrible. Okay. Uh, of course they
have their shake that has, you know,
basically sugar, chocolate, and butter.
That's it. Uh, they have their flat
liner fries with deep fried and pure
lard.
Then you get your candy, your soda, your
cigarettes, and your beer.
How nice.
Uh, here's an actual burger. What it
looks like. I think this is the four or
six. I don't know.
Okay, that sounds great. Um,
also they had a spokesperson
uh young young man who actually was 575
pounds
and uh he was 29 years old
when he passed away in 2011 at age of 29
from complications of pneumonia. not a
healthy person at age 29. He was a
spokesperson.
Spokesperson.
Um yeah, this this place was not a
healthy place at all. Uh yeah, this is
outside of the restaurant. Do you see
what's parked outside by the door? Do
you see?
Yeah. It's not functioning. It's just
for a show. Okay. It's an ambulance. Do
you see it?
Um, what else you guys? Um, they have a
coronary dog also in their menu. You see
it over there? Coronary dog by the shake
by the Yeah, the butter fat shake. Also
coronary dog. Great. What else?
They have an at least a warning on their
door that says caution. This
establishment is bad for your health. At
least they let you know. That's nice,
right?
Um because their other spokesperson
uh a gentleman that went also by patient
John
um also died
the same day he ate at the restaurant.
He had a heart attack later that day at
age 52. I think 2013 he passed away.
So that was patient John. Uh but Dr.
John is the owner. He went by Dr. John.
His real He wasn't a real doctor. Um he
just went by doctor. But it's all for
show. Like I said, he dressed like a
doctor, but he's not really a doctor. Um
yeah, it's all good. It's all Do you see
what's going on here? Uh so the the
if you go they'll put a uh hospital gown
on you because that's the requirement.
You have to wear a hospital gown to eat
there.
Yeah. So everybody wears a hospital
gown. What do you think?
Here are the uh waitresses. They all
dress like nurses.
And Oh yeah. And do you see what's on
the left? The picture, the left picture
is a scale. Let me go back. It's a
scale. It's a cattle scale because if
you weigh more than 350 lbs, you eat for
free.
All right. So, yeah, there it is. Full
of people.
That's what we promote or that's what
they promote anyway. Uh yeah, but that's
that's our country. Uh what's going on?
What has been going on for a few decades
now? What do you think?
Food manufacturers
including junk food people, restaurants,
everybody,
they know about this concept. Have you
ever heard of it?
The bliss point.
What's the bliss point? I'll tell you
what the bliss point is. I'll just
illustrate it in this way. Okay,
I'll just illustrate it. Let's pretend
you have a cup of coffee. I don't
recommend coffee, but this serves well
for the illustration because coffee is
bitter, right? So, if you have a cup of
coffee with no sugar,
you give it to people.
Most people won't really like it.
There's a weird person who drinks their
coffee with no sugar and they like it.
Okay. But most people are like, "H,
doesn't taste good." Right? But what
happens when you eat when you add a
teaspoon of sugar and you you know stir
give it to the person.
Okay, that tastes better.
What happens when you add two teaspoons
of sugar? Stir. Give it to the person.
Oh, that tastes much better. What
happens when you add three teaspoons of
sugar? Stir. Give it to the person.
Well, now we're talking. That tastes
really good. Most people like it between
two and three. Well, nowadays, who
knows? Because, you know, Starbucks puts
like 10. So, all these Frappuccinos or
whatever, they probably have changed
most people's palettes. So, most people
might need even more than three
teaspoons. Who knows? But, you know,
normal people, I guess two, three is
just about right, I guess.
But what happens if you put five
teaspoons of sugar?
For most people, that's too sweet. What
happens if you put 10 teaspoons of
sugar? Forget it.
I don't know about you, but I think most
people that would be too sweet.
So, do you see this curve over here? No
sugar, no pleasure. You put a little bit
more, more pleasure, more pleasure until
you reach the perfect amount and then
you put more and the pleasure starts
going down. Okay, let's talk about salt.
Just to give you an illustration, let's
say you have a pot of vegetable soup
that you're making at home. You put all
your veggies, your carrot, your onions,
your celery, your whatever.
Bunch of veggies. No salt.
Most people taste the soup.
Doesn't taste like much. Can we add a
little bit of salt? Okay, let's add a
tiny little pinch to big pot.
Well, that's not enough. Let's add a
little bit more. Okay, it starts going
up, right? The pleasure you feel when
you taste it.
Little bit more. Little bit more. Little
bit more. Okay. Boom. Perfect. This is
good.
But let what happens when you add the
whole salt shaker into the pot?
Too much. It's too salty.
So, do you see how it goes up up up?
Perfect. And then you add more and then
it starts going down, right? So,
for every food, hear me out. For every
manufactured food, every processed
product, you go to the supermarket, you
go to the grocery store, there's
thousands,
literally thousands of products there
from companies that hire
food scientists.
That's what they do. They engineer this
food.
This is what they do, you guys.
They manufacture, they engineer the
food. They calculate the bliss point for
every single product. With the fat,
the curve doesn't look like this.
The fat, it looks like this.
The more the better.
You're never going to eat fat all by
itself. As long as you combine it with
sugar or starch,
the more the better. the fat adds to the
mouth feel. If it's crunchy or if it's
creamy, then it's creamy. You know what
I mean? It's either crunchy or creamy.
The more the better.
That's what they do. They calculate it.
They know exactly what they're doing.
That's what they do to make the food as
palatable. That's what they'd say.
Palatable as possible. They're not going
to say addictive, obviously not. So,
this is what they do to stimulate the
brain. They know what it does to your
brain.
They know.
They know. It's It's not a secret to
them. It's not a secret. These foods are
made intentionally.
intentionally.
I know it sounds like a conspira con
like a conspiracy. It's not. It's simple
economics.
They're corporations, you guys. They
have to sell more every quarter. It's
Wall Street. They have to respond to
Wall Street, not to you, not to your
doctor.
Who do they have to respond to?
Wall Street.
That's who they have to respond to. They
have to sell more every quarter. How are
they going to do it? How do you think
they're going to do it?
How are they going to get people to buy
more and more and more and more?
Average consumption of Americans
3600 calories per person. That means
every child, every adult, every woman,
every man, everybody. I don't eat 3,600
calories. I can tell you that much.
Somebody's eating
my calories. Not every not all 3,600
calories, obviously, but somebody's
eating my share.
Maybe if yours too,
and they have to eat more next quarter.
This is simple economics. It's not a
conspiracy.
So they have to make the food as
palatable as say addictive. So Yale
University,
Yale,
they've studied this. They have a center
for obesity studies or something rather.
They have made a scale
of addictiveness of foods. They really
did this because they've studied how
addictive the foods are. They made a
scale of addictiveness
and Michigan, I think the University of
Michigan took that scale. They did a
study with their own students and they
found the 20 most addictive foods in the
country. You want to know what's number
one? Tell me what do you think
out of these foods?
What do you think is the most addictive
food in the country? What do you think?
Put in the chat.
They're promoting death, says Eric.
This place is still running. Yes, it is
running. I looked it up just before this
presentation because I wanted to know.
They're still running. They have a
website. The website doesn't have their
menu. It's weird. So weird. They're
weird. I have to say they have a YouTube
channel with music videos. It's so
weird. Anyway, the unhealthier the
better it seems. Yes, because that's
what sells you guys says. I mean, yes.
Downward parabolic curve. Yeah, that's
what it looks like. Weird. Uh, they play
with the amounts of sugar, salt, and fat
more than normal amounts. That's
correct. That's exactly right, Emmy.
Wall Street and taste buds. Yes. Yes,
that's right. And that is why the food
tastes weird when you eat them
separately.
That isn't true.
So,
nobody has guessed yet. What is the most
addictive food?
Number one, do you want to know? Do you
want me to tell you
what is the most addictive food?
Okay,
are you ready?
It's here. It's one of these.
Okay. If you guys are not going to tell
me, I'll tell you. Or has anyone said
maybe? Yes. Oh, I'm not even looking.
Sorry, you guys. Okay. Somebody said
hamburgers and fries. Okay. Somebody
said soda.
Nobody said potato chips. Somebody said
it. Woohoo.
Robert for the win. Robert said it.
Robert said it. Pizza. That's right, you
guys.
Numero uno.
Do you see it right here?
Number one,
pizza. Number two is chocolate. Emmy,
you got number two.
Fast foods are right here. See so many.
Eric, look at you. You got it. Because
fast food's all over the place. Pizza is
a fast food if you think about it.
Fries, cheeseburgers,
they're here. Chick fried chicken is a
fast food if you think about it. Can you
believe it?
Poison soy sauce. I lied to myself when
I says at least I'm not using salt.
It's a lot of sodium. I you can get low
sodium soy sauce. Uh soy sauce. Also, I
recommend getting Brax liquid aminos.
That's a better choice for soy sauce.
So, junk food. Yes. All over the place.
You see right here? My goodness.
Pizza and chocolate are my weakness,
Robert. Well, now you know why. It's not
your fault. It's not your fault.
They hook you. They hook you and they
know what they're doing.
Do you know why? So, okay, you guys, why
do you think pizza is number one? Why?
What's in pizza?
What are the ingredients? Think about
this.
Processed foods. Yes. Okay, Eric, you're
right. All of these are processed foods.
All of them except well, let's see.
Cereal, popcorn. Well, popcorn is
somewhat processed, but they, you know,
popcorn they put butter, salt, so yeah,
it's processed. So, rolls, cheese, every
single thing. Steak. Well, steak. H
meat. I guess it's not processed, but
it's meat. All right. Chocolate, ice
cream, cookies. Everything is processed
here. All right.
um made chocolate a chocolate pizza.
They made a chocolate pizza kill you
faster. Wow. The dough has sugar. Tomato
sauce has sugar. Very good, Robert.
Thank you. Yes, you are correct. But
ah did you know
I don't know how many of you know this
and I don't mean to offend anybody.
Please don't get mad at me. I'm just the
messenger you guys. But did you know
that the cheese in the in the Okay, the
casing is the protein
chocolate pizza. Yeah, I know you guys.
Crazy. Cheese. There you go. Cheese.
Robert, thank you. The cheese.
Okay, so when they make So the milk has
two types of protein,
casein and whey, right? In the process
of making cheese, they concentrate the
casing and the way is a leftover. Now
they know how to make money out of it
because they sell it to you as a powder
and you're like, "Oh, I'm going to go to
the gym." And you buy, you know, that's
how they get you to spend your money
now. Okay. The casing is the protein
left behind when the or the protein that
makes the cheese and it gets
concentrated
in cheese.
So cheese has much more concentrated
casein than the milk, right?
We already talked about casein in
cancer. Go and watch that
if you want to know what it does
regarding cancer. Go watch that
presentation. Okay, that's cancer. What
does it do in regards to addiction?
Did you know that when this protein is
digested,
it gets d becomes another molecule
called quesomorphine.
Quesomorphine.
What does that sound like to you?
[Music]
It's an opiate. An opiate.
Much milder than morphine of course, but
opiate nonetheless.
That's why you think of cheese stretchy.
Yummy.
Some people have a harder time
quitting cheese than meat.
When I go to churches, I kind of kid
around with people and I say, you know,
a lot of Adventists become chesitarians.
Just saying. Don't get offended. I'm
just saying. I'm just joking you guys.
Okay. Why other reasons? Refined flour.
Somebody said the dough sugar. Well,
flour itself is a refined carbohydrate
and it acts just like sugar.
The sauce definitely has sugar, real
sugar in it. It's a high calorie density
food. All high calorie density foods by
nature will be addictive.
Cheese is a c morphine from cow. That's
correct. That's right. And cheese is
cancer-causing. Yes. If you haven't seen
that presentation, highly recommend
watching it. Okay, now what about the
chocolate?
Sorry to give you the bad news if you
don't want to hear it.
I guess you can close your ears for the
next two minutes. Or do you want me to
tell you even?
Well, okay.
Sorry to give you the bad news, but here
it is.
Obviously, the chocolate has sugar and
fat combined.
That in and it of itself is addictive.
It has caffeine.
If you didn't know, surprise, surprise.
Chocolate has caffeine. Small amount,
but it has caffeine nonetheless.
More amount or higher amount of theob
broine. Theobo bromine is another brain
stimulant. It's much milder than
caffeine, but caffeine has 10 times more
of it than caffeine.
So there you go. Combination of both.
Then number four, it has phenolthyl
ethylamine. What the what in the world's
phenolethylamine? I'll tell you.
Phenolthylamine is a small molecule and
like it's alphylanate
alpha methylated
derivative. Do you know want to know
what it's alphylated
derivative is? Oh, it's a substance
called amphetamine.
Oh wow. Okay. So amphetamine is derived
of phenolethylamine.
Well, it has stimulating effects that
lead to the release of biogenic
amines such as dopamine.
There it is. So anyway, it's a
stimulating for the it's a stimulating
substance for the brain. That's all you
need to know. Don't even remember you
don't need to remember the name. All you
need to know is stimulating. The last
one, number five, anandmide.
What in the world is anandmide? Want to
know? Okay. Anandmide is a brain lipid
that binds to, listen up,
canabonoid
receptors.
Canabenoid.
What does that sound like? canaboninoid
receptors and mimics
the psychoactive
effects of plant derived
canabonoids.
What does that sound like to you?
Plantderived
canabonoids.
Do you see now why chocolate
is so yummy?
Cannabis. That's right, Robert.
Does that apply to cocoa as well? Yes.
All of these substances come from cocoa
except for the sugar.
The sugar is the one thing they have to
add because cocoa or co cacao is the
original substance that chocolate is
made out of. Cocoa is just the toasted
cacao let's say. But cacao is extremely
bitter. So sugar in huge amounts are
added to cocoa cacao to make it taste
palatable.
Everything else is part of the actual
plant.
Hemp weed.
That's right you guys. So there. Okay.
So let's finish this up.
If you are like me
terribly addicted to sweets or used to
be anyway,
what do you do?
How do you get out of this trap?
How you supposed to survive life?
Even when you do go to church, you guys,
every single potluck,
churches
have
I think I said it last time, the table.
You know what I mean when I say the
table? Because you have the other
tables, regular tables with the yummy
food. Even I I get invited to do health
seminars and some churches
are nice enough to have healthy food in
their potlucks when I go out sweet. They
have nice, you know, salads, you know,
nice whatever. But there's always the
table over there.
You know what I mean by the table?
Some of you know what I mean.
It's like crack cocaine over there.
For some people at least, not everybody
who drinks alcohol becomes alcoholic.
Not everybody who eats sweets becomes a
food addict,
but some people do.
So some people who go to church, there's
a crack cocaine over there. I'm just
saying. All right. So what to do?
Well, the first thing is just like
the 12 steps. First, you have to
recognize it's a problem.
It's a problem.
It could be an addiction or at least a
very bad habit at the very least. It's
the dessert table. See, you guys know
what I'm talking about.
Oh, somebody asked, "How about the
effects of dark chocolate?" Dark
chocolate is even more concentrated in
caffeine, in the broine, all of the
things. It's just more concentrated.
It does have more of the
uh antioxidants
but also has more of the stimulants. So
you have to weigh the pros and cons.
All right. Step number one, even 12step
programs, you have to recognize you have
a problem.
Number two
is
practice
abstinence.
Practice marijuana. In the beginnings, I
would always feel sick the next day
after church.
Emmy says that's why I stopped eating
the potlock. Oh my goodness. I would
take my own food. That's very smart.
That's a very smart thing to do. Darth
Vader said that table.
I didn't say it. I didn't say it. Darth
Vader said that table. Well,
you're not wrong. Some of those churches
says it looks like Darth Vader did it.
I'm not
I'm just saying.
I'm just saying. Marijuana and that
table. Yeah, chocolate.
All right, you guys. It's smart to take
your own food, even your own dessert if
you need to, you know,
abstinence.
I just want to read you a very famous
quote,
very famous. Hopefully, you know this
quote. I'm going to blow it up so that
we can all see it. Let me see. There it
is.
Pure air. This is from Ministry of
Healing, page 127.
Pure air.
Number one. Number two. Sunlight.
Number three.
Do you see that word right there? Number
three. Oldfashioned way to say
abstinence.
Abmiousness.
Whoa.
What in the world is obstinius?
It's just abstinence, said the old way.
Rest, exercise, proper diet, the use of
water, trust in divine power.
These are the true what?
The true what?
The true remedies.
These are the eight principles of
health, you guys, that our church has
been teaching for over 100 years.
And abstinence is one of the eight
principles of health.
It's one of them. is one of the true
remedies.
Absence is one of the eight true
The eight principles of health. The new
start principles.
It's one of them. Did you know? Did you
remember? Did you forget?
Let me show you what it does to the
brain.
Remember this image
all the way in the left is a healthy
brain.
In the middle we see an addict. Remember
how the addict had no dopamine
receptors. Remember that?
That's why it's missing the orange or
the red. remember right now. Look at the
brain over here on the right. Let me
make myself Okay, look at the brain on
the right.
It says after 14 months of what, you
guys?
14 months of what?
Abstinence. Look at the top of the
slide. Brain what?
What does it say the title? Brain what?
Brain recovery.
The brain can recover.
The brain. Let me repeat it. This is
very important. In fact, this is
crucial. This is the best thing you can
ever hear. This is great news for anyone
who is addicted to anything.
This is great news. This is great news.
Amen. Amy. Amen. Praise the Lord. The
Lord made our brains plastic. Meaning it
can heal. It can recover.
Recovery with abstinence. Yes, Robert.
Thank you. Recovery with absence. He
gave us the solution. And he gave us the
remedy,
the cure.
Abstinence is one of the eight
principles of health. There is the true
remedy.
14 months of abstinence. What do you see
in this brain?
What do you see back?
Do you see the red back?
The person is recovering
their dopamine receptors.
It clears the body from the toxins. Yes,
thank you Emmy. Yes, that is correct.
The body can heal. The brain can heal if
we give God a chance. You have to give
God a chance.
He gave us the true remedies. That's the
foundation for health
to the law and the testimony. That is
the truth. Don't look at anywhere else.
Look at that first. The dopamine
receptors, yes, I mean, the dopamine
receptors are coming back because God is
healing this brain. The person might not
even know, of course, that God is
healing this brain. They might not even
know. They might not even know, but it's
one of the eight.
Isn't that amazing? Praise the Lord.
Praise the Lord.
I'm just so happy we're part of this
wonderful
group people that has this message.
Number three, adequate nutrition. What
nutrition? Yes, of course we're talking
about food. Food food addiction, but
even all addictions honestly add the
nutrition is so important. Why? Because
when it comes to food, you need to
nurture your body with vitamins,
minerals, phyitochemicals, antioxidants.
I don't know about you, but I've been
watching Netflix lately. I had forgotten
about the
terrible, terrible show back in the
early 2000s called The Biggest Loser. I
don't know if you ever watched it.
That terrible show. It made people lose
weight. Extreme extreme weight loss. I
don't know if you've been watching. It's
horrible. Okay. But it did remind me
that people that used to weigh, you
know, 300 lb, whatever, would eat, you
know, to get to that kind of, you know,
uh, obesity, some people would eat 5,000
uh, uh, calories a day. There was also
another show back then called uh what
was it? Uh 600 lb life. I've mentioned
it before, I think. My 600 lb life. And
I remember them mentioning 10,000
calories a day. How in the world can you
eat that many calories? Well, here's the
thing. When you're eating junk food,
there's a reason why they call it empty
calories. You can be eating 5,000,
6,000, 7,000, 10,000 calories a day and
still be deficient in these things
because it's empty calories. You're not
getting enough vitamins, minerals,
antioxidants, phyitochemicals. Your body
is still deficient. So, your body is
still craving food.
You need to nurture your body
appropriately with enough nutrition.
That's part of it. It's not all of it,
but it's part of it. Also, this food has
fiber. Fiber provides bulk.
It fills you up.
Junk food does not.
But oil.
Oil is very, very concentrated in
calories. It uses very little volume.
Fiber is bulk. It fills you up. The
vegetables have very low calorie
density.
100 calories per pound. Oil is 4,000
calories per pound. Literally the most
calorie dense food of all.
See the difference?
So, we have to eat in the more
nutrient density side of the scale. Now,
most people nowadays are trying to eat
keto diet, carnivore diet.
I say those are the worst when it comes
to food addiction, when it comes to
weight loss, for diabetes is the worst.
The worst of all,
I'll tell you why. For food addiction in
particular, I think I mentioned it for
diabetes pri previously, but for food
addiction,
when you eat a high protein diet, it
turns out that
the amount of one amino acid goes down
in your brain because this amino acid is
the hardest one to absorb into the
brain. It's called tryptophan
and it competes with other amino acids
for absorption into the brain. And when
you eat a lot of meat or a lot of animal
protein, there's too many of other amino
acids in those foods. So tryptophan gets
left behind. It's too much competition.
So the amount of tryptophan in the brain
actually goes down with a high protein
diet. And I'm talking about animal
proteins. There's too much competition
with other amino acids. The amount of
tryptophan in the brain goes down.
It just so happened that tryptophan is
the precursor for serotonin.
And serotonin,
as you might know, with low amounts of
serotonin,
people might get depression.
And people with depression tend to eat
more, eat more, eat more. So, it's not a
good idea to eat high protein, highfat,
low carb diets. It's well known that
people who go on keto might get
irritability, for instance.
It's not a good idea. You might crave
carbs even more.
With the more carbs, and of course, I
would recommend the good carbs.
Tryptophan levels go up, serotonin
levels go up, and you feel a lot better.
But I would eat the good carbs because
people with food addictions have to be
careful with sugar and flour.
These can be triggers to eat more. So
you have to avoid refined carbohydrates.
The those are the worst the worst things
are the refined sugars and the flour.
Flour even flour
is like sugar. All right. Okay. So, next
thing to do is to follow all eight of
the healthpromoting
uh the healthpromoting habits. So, all
eight of the principles of health. Uh
so, one time I I was asked to compare
the all eight of our health promoting uh
principles of health with the six from
the American College of Lifestyle
Medicine.
Um and they're very similar because even
now the medical community recognizes
the importance of our principles of
health. They're based on science. Now
that means that we have to create new
habits just like I talked last week. So
this is from last week. Just a reminder
of the importance of forming habits,
good habits like exercise, like eating
salads or whatever. These are should
become habits. So they are automatic.
Okay, automatic. Remember how we talked
about this last week. Put a new hab. If
you take something away, you have to put
something in there. Otherwise, you
create a vacuum. Don't create vacuums.
If you take something out, put something
new in there. Uh a good thing, you know?
So, put a good a good So, if you take
sodas out, maybe put uh string uh
sparkling water in or something, you
know what I mean? So something to fill
that vacuum um and not just leave a
vacuum there. And of course try to make
those automatic like exercises. So when
you don't do it, you're like, "Oh,
something is missing." Just like
brushing your teeth, it should be just
like that. So it becomes automatic. So
when you don't do it, something's
missing. And we talked about planning
last week too. And even today we
mentioned it so that you don't end up
running to McDonald's, you know, when
you're too hungry, lunch or dinner. Last
week I mentioned make like a little
spreadsheet or something for the week if
necessary and plan ahead your breakfast,
dinner, lunch and dinner, even the days
you're going to exercise, what kind of
exercise, all of this so that you know,
put it in the calendar. Make it
non-negotiable.
If you're like, "Oh, let's go to this or
that. Let's go uh shopping at the mall."
No, no, no, no. I have an appointment at
the gym. You know, whatever. Make it
non-negotiable.
Make it because your health is more
important. If you're not there for your
family, who's going to be there for your
family? That's got to be a priority.
Okay. Next is get enough health uh
sleep. Because by not getting enough
sleep, you alter your appetite hormones.
I didn't put the slides. I should have
put the slides that show that when you
don't get enough sleep, your appetite
hormones are out of whack and you get
more appetite
and you get hungry and you gain weight
and you put yourself at higher risk for
diabetes.
So, don't skip the sleep.
You need seven hours minimum if you're
an adult.
If you're a child or teenage, you need
minimum 8 to 10.
You could not skip on this. If you want
to have self-control,
you have to have it or else you're going
to be hungry and that's bad for food
addiction, right? Intermittent fasting,
which you're a food addict. you have to
first do everything else so that you
have you have you you have a food uh you
have a good foundation because fasting
can be triggering for some people but if
you have everything already and you're
in good shape you can do uh intermittent
fasting because watch this okay this is
amazing it's hard to believe but look at
what it says okay look these people ate
this study they did at the obesity
society obesity society okay
and they did this thing called early
time restricted feeding, which is the
intermittent fasting that you eat early.
Not the kind you start at noon and end
at 8. That's terrible.
No bueno. Okay, look at this. They start
eating at 8, they end at 2.
Two.
But look at what it says right there
inside of the circle. Restricted eating
8 to two. improves fat burning. Okay,
that's great. At night
and reduces hunger swings.
Reduces hunger swings.
That's very important. If you want more
self-control and less food addiction,
you're not going to believe this. Or
maybe you already know. In that case,
you are going to believe it.
Look at this, you guys. I'm going to
blow it up a little so you can see
better.
Look,
same times. This is a different study al
together, but it's the same time.
Same time. Okay, 8 to two. Look at the
benefits.
Okay, first on the on the left, it's
talking about insulin. So, this is great
for uh for diabetics because it improves
your sens sensitivity to insulin. So
that's why they're they're they're
making less insulin. They have better
insulin sensitivity. Their pancreas is
working better. That's what's all all
the stuff on the left over here. It's
and on the right it says blood pressure
went down. Oxidative stress went down.
So all the damage in the body. So their
uh inflammation all that stuff went
down. But look what it says about
appetite. Do you see? Are you looking?
Appetite in the evening went down you
guys.
They're they're less hungry in the
evening even though they're not eating
in the evening.
By the way, it says they're fasting
triglycerides went up. People get, "Oh,
no. This terrible." That's because
they're burning fat in the morning.
Remember the thing about furning burning
fat in the morning.
So, their fat is mobilized. They're in
fat oxidation,
meaning they're burning fat. So, the fat
shows up in the morning in their blood.
That's what's happening. Okay. But I
wanted to show you the appetite aspect
of it. Their appetite goes down in the
evening.
That's very important.
That's very, very beneficial.
It's crazy. Look at this. Did I show you
this before? No, I don't think so. Okay,
look at the dark bars.
Those are the people who are fasting.
The white bars are the people who are
not fasting.
Pay attention.
Desire to eat all the way in the left,
top left. Desire to eat in the evening.
Dark bar. Do you see it? Dark bar in the
evening is way lower in the people who
fasted
and they're not eating in the evening.
How is it possible their desire to eat
is lower? Same thing in capacity to eat.
In other words, they're too they can't
even eat.
Their capacity to eat is lower in the
evening. The people who are not eating
in the evening, they stopped eating at
2. Their hunger, see the right, top
right, in the evening is lower than the
people who are eating.
They're less hungry than the people who
are actually eating. Okay. Bottom left.
This is how do you explain this you
guys? How do you explain this?
The people who are fasting are feeling
fuller than the people who are eating in
the evening.
Look,
I didn't I didn't make this up. It's in
the data. It's in the research.
the stomach fullness
is they feel fuller
and it's all of all of this is happening
because fasting helps
your appetite hormones
including GLP1. By the way, do you know
what GLP1 is? GLP1.
Have you ever heard of ompic wovi?
That's what those medications do. They
cost $1,000 a month. Fasting does the
same thing.
I'm just saying.
And Ellen White said without knowing any
of this science over 100 years ago, it's
better to eat two meals instead of
three. What? Two meals, breakfast and
lunch.
If she wasn't inspired by God, then what
was it?
How did she know?
I don't know.
Okay, so you guys are saying, "I've been
diabetic type one since I was three, and
I learned about triglycerides and
glycemic a few years ago. I wish I knew
about these when I was a teen." Yeah.
Yeah,
I hope you watched the series. We did a
series on diabet on diabetes.
Everything has this blue light to
disturb our sleep rhythm. I hope you're
covering it with tape or something or
put a book in front of it because you're
right. Uh hopefully we don't have any
lights to disturb our sleep. That's very
very true. Okay, let's finish up you
guys. The next thing is to incorporate
strength training because that is the
best way to change
your metabolism.
By incorporating strength training, I
think we talked about this before,
you are changing to a healthier
metabolism like the one on the left with
more muscle mass. And that is super
important in order to uh increase the
metabolism
so that you have a healthier weight.
Most people who have food addiction
sometimes they're triggered by
restricting calories. That's how it all
starts. And they're restricting calories
because they're dieting and they're
dieting the very unhealthy way.
How do you solve all of this? By having
healthy weight in the first place. And
so you if you're eating healthy and
you're exercising the correct way, you
are not going to need to restrict
calories. See how it all starts from
just the beginning. If we're doing it
the right way from the beginning, eating
right and exercising, none of this would
happen.
But we go on these unhealthy extreme
diets. We starve ourselves and then we
end up binging later. And then we end up
binging on high calorie, high sugar
foods.
And then we go in this cycle of eating
these unhealthy foods and then we starve
ourselves and then we binge again and we
and everything goes out of whack.
It's bad. By the way, this kind of uh
exercise you can do at any age. Oh no,
I'm too old to go to the gym. No.
No. This lady from Linda, California.
Want to know what age she is in this
picture?
Want to guess?
101.
If she can do it, you can do it.
By the way, if you're older than 65, you
should be doing it
because anyone older than 65, their
highest risk is a fall.
And once you fall, your risk for dying
is way higher.
Anyone who's an adult should be doing it
if they're not. I think I mentioned last
time if you're if if you haven't done
any resistance exercise,
Google power up in 10. It's free from
the state of California, from the power
department of health. It's the PDF.
Download it. Anyone can do it.
I was told eating nuts at night troubles
your sleep. Nobody should be eating
anything heavy at night because
if you're eating at night, here's what
happens. You have food in your stomach.
Therefore,
your
all the energy that should be going into
cleansing, into repairing of tissues,
detoxing your brain, all of this energy
is going to go into digesting the food.
None of the repair the or you know some
of it will but not all of the energy
that should be going into the reparation
rejuvenation detoxification
some of that energy is going to be
diverted.
So all the healing that should be
happening at night is not going to be
happening. Your stomach should be empty
when you go to bed. So no digestion in
the stomach should be happening because
otherwise some of that energy is going
to be diverted.
So no, no one should eat before going to
bed. Hopefully more than four hours
should have should be uh in between
sleep and eating. Hopefully more than 4
hours before.
Okay. Uh so I would not recommend eating
before going to sleep. Definitely not.
And uh let's see what else. If you don't
like going to the gym, how about some of
this then?
It's kind of like going to the gym,
doing some of the gardening. That's if
you have some, you know, space to do it,
obviously. But if you have a garden, you
get tomatoes
and some veggies or whatever, and you
get to work out. Not too bad, right?
Okay. Last but not least, if you have
serious
addiction issues,
seek help.
Do it because sometimes you're not going
to be able to do it by yourself. Some of
that brain damage
is serious
and the
part about uh self-control, willpower,
all of that is now gone. You might need
professional help. Of course, you need
the help of God first of all, and God
might direct you to the right person.
Seek first the kingdom of God and his
righteousness,
and all these things shall be added to
you.
He will direct you. He will show you the
right path.
But there are some addictions that need
professional help. I don't know if you
know this, but for for instance, some
people who are addicted to alcohol, if
they quit on their own, it could be
lethal in some cases.
So, there are some, you know,
professional help, behavioral therapy,
support groups. Some people need to be
hospitalized, some people might need
medication. Even therapy, I think, is
very, very important for some people.
So,
same with food addiction. It might be
very helpful to get therapy, counseling,
overeaters, anonymous groups. There's
such a thing, you know. So, group med uh
group support, whatever is needed in
some serious cases, seek it and get it.
Okay, I'm going to finish with this.
Um, so whatever you eat or drink or
whatever you do, do it all to the glory
of God. Another reminder
that the health message which includes
of course nutrition, what we eat, the
diet, but also exercise, also sleep,
rest, right? Also water also
obviousness
also known as abstinence today or
temperance which true temperance is to
abstain from all things that are bad and
the good things do it with moderation.
That's what true temperance is. Not all
things in moderation. No, no, no, no,
no, no, no. That's Satan's temperance
that wants you to do the bad things in
moderation, too. No, no, no. True
temperance is doing good things in my
donation and abstain from bad things.
That's true temperance.
So all of these things
are part of the health message.
And all of them whether you drink, eat,
whatever you do, do it to the glory of
God.
And doing those things to the glory of
God, to glorify God is part of the three
angels message
more relevant than ever today.
Today in preparation for
the last
uh scenes of Earth's history today.
Nowadays,
now more than ever, the world out there,
people out there are sick. Especially
after CO,
pandemic might be over, but CO is not
gone. CO is not gone and still causing
trouble. People are getting sicker and
sicker and sicker because every time we
expose ourselves to it, we get sicker.
So, people need help. People need this
message. People need to know how to take
care of their body. People need to know
how to
overcome
this.
People need help.
We have
the message. You know, it's amazing. I
work with so many nonvenists and they
all know about Lumalinda. They all know
about the blue zones. They all know
about the advent studies. They all know
that they think we all do it. You guys,
they have a way over inflated um
uh view of Adventist. We have to live up
to it. It's time. It's time. It's time
because they need it.
It could be our ministry. If you guys
are looking for a ministry, here's an
idea.
Start a support group. Start a cooking
class once a month, once a week,
whatever. Start something.
And invite people. Invite your friends.
Invite your co-workers. Invite your
family.
Show them. Show them how to heal. They
can heal their brain, their body, their
mind, their soul. And God can help them.
We do have a sickening lifestyle but God
is our healer and our savior.
So I want to invite you to
to uh pray so that we can end our
presentation for today. I want to thank
everyone. Your participation
has been super nice and valuable and
very engaging.
Thank you for for your comments. They've
been very on point. Thank you so much.
Uh yeah, you guys are great. Thank you
so so much.
And uh let's end with a prayer. And you
can share this. Feel free to share
all the information that I have um uh
that I have shared with you. Feel free
to use it. Yeah. Use it. Use it for your
own presentations. Yeah.
Have a little, you know, at home get
together and present it. Have a little
discussion afterwards if you want.
Anything. Uh it could be a a great
conversation starter even. So, all
right, let's have some prayer. Let's
pray. Thank you, Lord, for this evening.
Thank you for the opportunity
to share this information.
Forgive us Lord if we have not glorified
our bodies. If we have not glorified you
through our bodies. If we have not taken
care of our bodies
as we should as the temple for your Holy
Spirit.
Help us, Lord, to take that decision, to
make that decision, to take the to take
this message and take it to those who
need it,
to
be your hands and feet.
There's so much misinformation out
there. Lord,
help us to take the truth,
the true health message, the one that
can really heal, the true remedies
out to those who need it.
If we if we need to be the ones to start
something,
guide us, Lord.
Give us your wisdom.
Show us what we need to do.
be with all of us tonight. All of those
who are connected tonight, all of those
who will watch this in the future.
I ask for your Holy Spirit to guide
them, to heal them if they need to be
healed. for anyone in their family that
might need healing. Lord, I ask you to
be with them as well and be with us the
rest of this week
and uh for the rest of the members of of
Living Mana online church. Bless this
church, Lord. In Jesus name we pray.
Amen.
Amen. And amen. And thank you for for
sticking around. And I know it's a
little long, but I really wanted to to
to share this with you because I think
it's so important. Share, like this
video, and share this video so that way
more people get to know and engage with
the channel so it gets, you know, more
views and stuff. But thank you again.
Thank you for being with us. Thank you
for for all your support. And uh two
more weeks. I'll just give you the date
once uh so that you are ready. Uh it'll
be the 16th, September 16th. I will
announce what will be the the topic
because I forgot now but it will be
September 16th. So tell your friends to
connect and thank you once again for
being here and
God bless you.
God bless you everyone.
Bye bye. Good night.